A Guide to the Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, 1793-1874
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, 1793-1874
Library of Virginia
7 volumes.
Richmond County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled. please check alternative form available heading for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Richmond County in 2004.
Alternative Form Available
Please see Richmond County Microfilm index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.
Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger, 1847-1852 is available as microfilm Richmond County (Va.) Reels 221 and 222
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Business Records, both volumes and loose records are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safekeeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business records exhibit appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments. These records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debt suits, and contract disputes.
Lost Records Note: During the burning of Richmond on April 3, 1865, during the Civil War, Richmond circuit court judge John A. Meredith led efforts to save the circuit court records found at the State Court House. Rescuers successfully removed all the papers that were necessary to pending suits and many of the order books, but all of the wills and deed books were lost. Records of the superior court and circuit superior court of law and chancery were also destroyed. Most of the pre-Civil War Hustings Court records exist.
Locality History: Richmond County was named either for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for the late-seventeenth-century duke of Richmond. It was formed from old Rappahannock County in 1692. Its area is 193 square miles, and the county seat is Warsaw.
Scope and Content
Richmond County (Va.) Business Records, 1793-1874, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Richmond City (Va.). Represented records largely consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, journals, letter book, minute books and subscription books.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Glenn and Brother Daybook, 1849-1851
Series II: Mangorike Wharf Company Minutes and Subscription Book, 1873-1874
Series III: Moody and Price Letter Book, 1793-1796
Series IV: Plummer and Tapscott Journal, 1812-1814
Series V: Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger, 1847-1852
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: Richmond County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1748-1958
Additional Richmond City (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Glenn and Brother Daybook, 1849-1851, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Glenn and Brother was a general store that conducted business in Farnham Church, Richmond County, Virginia, during the mid-nineteenth century. One of the owners was Matthew Glenn, Jr. Richmond County may have been named for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for Charles Lennox, first duke of Richmond and a son of King Charles II. It was formed from Old Rappahannock County in 1692. The county seat is Warsaw. Some volumes were burned and mutilated through unknown causes; in addition, the will books prior to 1699 were missing as early as 1793, and order books for the period 1794-1816 are also missing. Numerous loose records prior to 1781 are missing as well.
  - Glenn and Brother Daybook 1849-1851
- Mangorike Wharf Company Minutes and Subscription Book, 1873-1874, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Mangorike Wharf Company was organized in 1873 in Richmond County, Virginia, for the purpose of building a wharf along the Rappahannock River.
  - Mangorike Wharf Company Minutes and Subscription Book, 1873-1874
- Moody and Price Letter Book, 1793-1796, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Moody and Price was a shipping company headquartered in the city of Richmond, Virginia, during the late eighteenth century. The letter book was perhaps used as an exhibit in a court case heard in Richmond County. Richmond County may have been named for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for Charles Lennox, first duke of Richmond and a son of King Charles II. It was formed from Old Rappahannock County in 1692. The county seat is Warsaw. Some volumes were burned and mutilated through unknown causes; in addition, the will books prior to 1699 were missing as early as 1793, and order books for the period 1794-1816 are also missing. Numerous loose records prior to 1781 are missing as well.
  - Moody and Price Letter Book, 1793-1796
- Plummer and Tapscott Journal, 1812-1814 First National Bank Ledger, 1812-1814, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Plummer and Tapscott was a general store that conducted business in Farnham Church, Richmond County, Virginia, during the early 19th century. Richmond County may have been named for Richmond borough in Surrey, England, or for Charles Lennox, first duke of Richmond and a son of King Charles II. It was formed from Old Rappahannock County in 1692. The county seat is Warsaw. Some volumes were burned and mutilated through unknown causes; in addition, the will books prior to 1699 were missing as early as 1793, and order books for the period 1794-1816 are also missing. Numerous loose records prior to 1781 are missing as well.
  - Plummer and Tapscott Journal 1812-1814
- Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger, 1847-1852, 3 volumes
  Historical Information: Robert B. Sydnor was a merchant who owned a general store in Richmond County, Virginia, during the mid-nineteenth century.
  - Robert B. Sydnor Journals and Ledger 1847-1852